Phillip: Communication is all about giving,
receiving, and sharing information but this must
be done clearly and effectively to be of value.
Different forms of communication are suitable
for different occasions, and there's no
one way that's better than all the others.
Maddy: So, how can you achieve clear
and effective communication using
the main forms of communication?
Let’s look at these whilst remembering
that different methods will often
be combined in different ways.
Phillip: Written communication, this includes
emails, handwritten memos, typed letters, digital
messages, SMS messages, and much more besides.
When using written communication, you need
to be precise, clear, and unambiguous.
Make sure you're being explicit with
what you want to communicate, and
don't leave it to interpretation.
It is therefore, important to review
everything you write before you send
it, just in case what you have written
doesn’t impart what you meant it to.
It is also important that when receiving written
communication, you make sure, you take the time
to read it carefully, so you don't miss anything.
Maddy: Oral communication includes
face-to-face conversations, phone calls,
video calls, and giving presentations.
When communicating orally you should make
sure that you speak slowly and clearly.
You don't want the other person to mishear you,
so make sure you're being precise with your words.
If you need to give someone a lot of
information this way, take your time, so as
not to overwhelm them by speaking too quickly.
And make sure you use language and
terminology that they'll understand.
Although all forms of communication
involve a back-and-forth, this is
especially true for oral communication.
It is therefore important to make sure the other
person has time to reply and ask questions,
and don't assume they've understood everything.
Gently ask them if they want you to clarify and
listen carefully to what they say at all times.
Phillip: Nonverbal communication
means communicating "without words".
Typically, it's about body
language and appearance.
It's your facial expressions, your tone of voice,
and what you're doing with your arms and legs.
It's everything you're doing
except the writing or speaking.
Try to be aware of things like posture and stance.
It's important to appear confident and
calm, but also be wary of appearing
physically imposing or defensive.
Try to be aware of your expressions too.
Sometimes when we're having a difficult
conversation, it's easy to say a lot with
just how your face looks, so it’s essential
that your body language matches your words.
Nonverbal communication also includes
other things like the way you dress.
Think about the environment you're in
and who you're going to be speaking to,
when deciding what you're going to wear.
What impression are you giving with your outfit?
Maddy: Visual communication is when images
or video are used to communicate information.
This is often used along with words or speech.
For example, including graphs
or animations in a presentation.
The important thing is that the
visual element of communication
should complement the other elements.
Sometimes people will include visual
elements which can distract attention
and don't enhance the message or contain
any relevant information on their own.
Communication today has become more visual
in general, especially with the use of
digital media, but it is also important
that imagery is not overused, so that
the message gets lost or misinterpreted.
Phillip: Listening.
Understanding how communication takes place can
help you to communicate more effectively, and
as you learn to communicate more effectively,
you start to understand how listening
is an important part of communication.
Active listening is a way of effectively engaging
with those who are communicating with you and
is an important part of the negotiating process.
By letting others speak and showing that
you understand what they are saying, by
the way you respond to, both verbally
and nonverbally, helps ensure that
effective communication is taking place.
So, we can see that communication can take place
in numerous ways but unless you understand what
is being communicated to you, and you can show
that you have understood that communication,
then it is not going to be effective.